[ANDREAS] Hi, everyone! I'm so glad to be here at LABitConf. This is my fourth.
[ANDREAS]大家好！我很高兴来到LABitConf。这是我第四次来这里
I think I've only missed one.
我想我只错过了一次聚会
Huge thanks to Rodolfo Andragnes, who opened [the event] with such passion and enthusiasm.
非常感谢Rodolfo Andragnes， 他以如此的热情拉开了这次活动序幕
I understood about half of it, because he speaks very fast in Spanish.
我只听懂了一半，因为他的西班牙语说得很快
My Spanish is still at the Duolingo 'level two' standard. I won't be doing my presentation today in Spanish.
我的西班牙语仍然是Duolingo的“二级”标准。我今天不会用西班牙语进行演讲
Maybe in two years. Every now and then I try to practice a bit with Duolingo.
也许两年后。我会尝试与Duolingo一起练习
It pops up little reassuring messages [such as],
它几乎不会弹出一些令人安心的消息[例如，
"More Americans are studying foreign languages on Duolingo than in public schools in America."
“在Duolingo上学习外语的美国人比在美国的公立学校里学习的还要多”
Great statistic, right? It would be true if only two people were using Duolingo;
很棒的统计数据，对不对？ 如果只有两个人在使用Duolingo就好了；
[American schools] don't really teach foreign languages, but -- you know -- we are trying there.
[美国学校]并不真正的教授外语， 但是-您知道-我们正在努力
Spanish will be my fourth language. I hope I can get to the level where I can order food in a restaurant...
西班牙语将是我的第四语言。我希望我能达到我可以在餐厅点菜的水平...
without embarrassing myself.
避免自己难堪
That is where [I am] at the moment. Not ready to [speak about] Bitcoin [in Spanish] quite yet.
当我来到这里，我还没有准备好[用西班牙语谈论]比特币
[But] I'm really excited to be here.
[但是]我很高兴来到这里
I would like to talk about a topic that keeps coming up [around] Bitcoin: black markets. [Haunted noise]
我想谈论一个关于比特币的热门话题：黑市 [闹鬼的声音]
You see, bitcoin is used for black markets. You have heard about that, yes? It is used for black markets.
您听过过吧，比特币被用于黑市。是吗？ 它被用于黑市
Of course, it is also used for some white markets too. In Argentina, it is used for some blue markets.
当然，它也用于某些正当的市场， 在阿根廷，它用于一些"蓝色市场"
["Blue market"] is what they renamed their black market because it is such a big part of the economy,
“蓝色市场”是他们对于黑市的叫法， 因为它是经济的重要组成部分
and they want it to sound more palatable.
他们希望它听起来更容易接受
Bitcoin is colorblind when it comes to markets. It doesn't distinguish between black and white markets,
比特币对于市场其实是个色盲， 它无法区分黑市和白市，
blue and gray, or any other colors in the rainbow of markets; it just serves markets.
蓝市和灰市，或其他任何颜色的市场， 它只是服务于市场
The real question is, what is the difference between a white market and a black market?
真正的问题是， 在白市和黑市之间有什么区别 ？
Is the color a good metric for us to understand [how these] markets function? I think it is a very poor metric.
颜色是我们了解这些市场功能的好指标吗？ 我认为这是一个非常差的指标
Calling a market "white" or "black" doesn't tell us much about what that market does or how well it works.
将市场称为“白色”或“黑色”并不能告诉我们这个市场是做什么的，也不能告诉我们它是如何运作的
The people who use [such] terms would really like you to think there are a whole set...
使用[这种]术语的人只是想要你认为有一整套......
of [moral] associations that go along with that color.
与该颜色相关的[道德]关联
'White markets are good, black markets are bad.' 'White markets are legal, black markets are illegal.'
“白市好，黑市坏。” “白市是合法的，黑市是非法的。”
'White markets are [functional], black markets are [dysfunctional].'
“白色市场是[功能性]的， 黑市是[功能失调]的
'White markets are fair, black markets are unfair.' 'White markets are safe, black markets are unsafe.'
“白市是公平的，黑市是不公平的。” “白市安全，黑市不安全。”
'White markets are moral, black markets are immoral.'
“白市是道德的，黑市是不道德的。”
Bullshit! [Laughter] [Applause]
胡说！ [笑声] [掌声]
Not a single one of those statements is true.
这些陈述中没有一个是正确的
White markets and black markets differ in only one essential component:
白市和黑市的区别只有一个基本点：
white markets are licensed, black markets are unlicensed. That is it.
白色市场有执照，黑色市场是没有执照。 就是这样
Black markets can be moral, safe, just, fair, and efficient; simultaneously, white markets can be immoral, unsafe,
黑市可以是道德的，安全的，公正的，公平的和有效的； 同时，白色市场可能是不道德，不安全的，
unjust, [unfair], and inefficient.
不公正，[不公平]和低效率
We all know this. [Subconsciously], we know it. The taxi cartel is a white market; Uber is a black market.
我们[潜意识里]都知道这一点，我们知道。 出租车卡特尔是一个白色市场。优步是一个黑市
I won't take a bloody taxi. I have been to fifty-three countries and robbed by taxi drivers in fifty-two.
我不会打出租车。我去过五十三个国家，在五十二个国家都被出租车司机中抢劫过
"The airport is here. My hotel is here." "Let's go that way!" [Dramatic, long-route loops]
“机场在这里。我的旅馆在这里。” “走那边吧！” [然后是绕来绕去的绕远路]
"On triple tariffs with seven extras that I just invented." This has happened to me in every country in the world.
“征收三项关税，加上刚发明的七项额外关税。” 世界上每个国家都发生过这样的事情
Why? Because it is a regulated, licensed guild. A cartel. It is an inefficient, broken market, full of corruption.
为什么？因为它是受管制的，需要执照的行业。一个卡特尔。这是一个效率低下，破碎的市场，充满了腐败
Uber works. It is efficient, fair, and transparent, but it is a black market.
而优步它高效，公平， 透明，但这是一个黑市
We don't call it a black market because it is run by a multinational corporation with nice graphics...
我们不称其为黑市，因为它是一家由具有精美图片宣传的跨国公司...
and [a ticker symbol on] the stock market index.
以及[股票代码]在纳斯达克上市
We don't really want to call it the black market, but it is, if it is not licensed.
我们真的不想称其为黑色市场，但如果未获得许可，它就是黑市
Right outside this place, there are cute little electric scooters with lime colors.
就在这个地方外面，有一些很可爱的小电动滑板车，是石灰色的
Have you tried those? They are so much fun.
你尝试过那些吗？他们是很有趣
You can go fifteen miles per hour on the sidewalk or the street; I'm sure one of the two is illegal, but not sure.
您可以在人行道上或街上以15英里/小时的速度行驶; 我觉得这是非法的，但不确定
You [must] wear a helmet -- I didn't, I'm sorry, that was probably illegal -- and the service itself is not licensed.
您[必须]戴头盔–对不起，我没有戴头盔， 那可能是非法的-并且该服务本身没有许可证
So that is a black market.
这就是黑市
In North Korea, you can only have one of six haircuts if you are a male, which means [mine] is a black market.
在朝鲜，如果您是男性，您剪发的时候只能在六种发型中选一种，如果理发店提供其它发型，那就是黑市
It is not one of the approved haircuts. [Laughter] I call it a haircut, but it is just the result of hair loss.
它不是批准的发型之一。 [笑声] 我称它为理发，但我这只是脱发而已
But I would still like to pretend for a few more years, while I can.
我还是要假装几年
There is nothing essentially moral about white markets, nothing essentially immoral about black markets.
白色市场本质上没有什么道德可言， 黑市本质上没有什么不道德的
General Dynamics selling cluster bombs to the Saudis is the whitest of white markets; it is not only legal,
通用动力公司向沙特阿拉伯出售集束炸弹 是白色市场中最白的；这不仅合法，
it is strongly encouraged [by the U.S. government] and I [am forced to] pay for some of it [as a] taxpayer.
[美国政府强烈鼓励]我[被迫]作为纳税人支付其中的一部分
Is it moral? Hell no, it isn't.
这是道德的吗？当然不是！
The person selling bananas on the street, without a merchant's license, is the black market. Is it moral?
在街上卖香蕉的人，没有工商局发放的执照，就是黑市。这是道德的吗？
Hell yes, it is.
是的，是的
Using bitcoin to escape a collapsing currency in Venezuela is highly illegal and a [grey] market.
在委内瑞拉，为了逃离正在崩溃的法币，人们使用比特币，这是绝对非法的，是一个[灰色]市场
Is it moral? It is a human right. It is not just moral, it is the obligation of a parent to protect their children,
这是道德的吗？这只是一项人权。不只是关乎道德，父母有义务保护自己的孩子，
[including] under the U.N. Convention for Human Rights.
（包括《联合国人权公约》）
[Yet] it is illegal, with heavy penalties. The things Maduro is doing? 'White market' everywhere!
[但是]这是非法的，会受到重罚。 马杜罗在做什么？ “白市”无处不在！
Perfectly legal, fully licensed, and completely broken.
完全合法，完全许可且完全被破坏了
The difference between white and black markets is an issue of licensing.
白市和黑市的区别，只是许可问题
What is the natural state of markets? The big gray [market] in between.
市场的自然状态是什么？ 是介于两者之间的大灰色[市场]
Grey markets don't emerge, they simply exist.
灰色市场不会出现，它们只会存在
In the absence of any other forms, all markets are grey.
在没有任何其他形式的情况下，所有市场都是灰色的
How do white markets emerge? You have a gray market in place and someone gives it a license. Now it is white.
白色市场是如何出现的？你有一个灰色市场，有人给了它许可证。那就是白市
[How do black markets emerge?] You have a gray market in place and someone makes it illegal. Now it is black.
[黑市如何出现的？]您有一个灰色市场，有人将其定为非法。那就是黑市
Markets [exist] anytime two [or more] individuals, without coercion and of their own free will,
市场在任何时候都[允许]交易双方， 在没有强迫的情况下，遵循自己的自由意志，
decide to transact and agree on a price they find [mutually] beneficial.
决定进行交易并就双方互惠的价格达成一致
That is a market. That is it. It doesn't have a color, didn't require permission, and doesn't need a license.
那才是真正的市场。这就对了。它没有颜色，不需要许可，也不需要许可证
It is a natural human activity that occurs everywhere, in every time, throughout history.
这是一种自然发生的人类活动 ， 遍及历史的每一个角落
But we want to invent new terms in order to somehow provide 'color' to these markets;
但是我们想发明新的术语，以便以某种方式为这些市场提供“色彩”；
legitimacy to some, illegitimacy to others.
对某些人合法，对另一些人不合法
What is the trajectory of every white market? Every white market starts off as a grey market.
每个白色市场的发展轨迹如何？ 每个白色市场都始于灰色市场
Then it gets licensed.
然后它获得许可
Initially, the licensing is sold to you as a way to enforce some kind of "good behaviour" standard or quality.
最初，许可证是作为强制执行的方式出售给您的某种“良好行为”标准或质量
After all, you want your doctors to be licensed, [right]? They always go back to that [example].
毕竟，您希望您的医生是有执照的，不是吗？他们总是回到那个例子
In some U.S. states, ten thousand or more professions require professional licensing.
在美国某些州，有上万个或更多专业需要专业许可
In Louisiana, the amount of hours you need to become a cosmetician that does [manicures or pedicures]...
在路易斯安那州，您成为一个整形师[修指甲或修脚]的化妆师 所需要的时间...
exceeds -- by four times -- the hours you need to become an emergency medical technician in an ambulance.
超过了救护车中的紧急医疗技术员四倍的时间
If you try to do nail [manicures] without a license,
如果您试图在没有许可的情况下修指甲[美甲]，
you will be arrested because you are operating in the black- red, teal, and sparkly [markets].
您将被捕 因为您在黑红色，蓝绿色和闪闪发光的[市场]中无照经营
Which [color] you choose is up to you, but you certainly don't have the requisite license.
选择哪种[颜色]取决于您的行为， 但是您当然没有必需的许可证
Gradually, guilds and "professional associations" form, whose primary purpose is to make sure...
逐渐地，行会和“专业协会”形成了， 其主要目的是确保...
there isn't [too much] competition, to keep out those who would try to emerge into the market [themselves].
消除（太多的）竞争，要排除那些试图进入市场的竞争者[除了自己以外]
Like the taxi cartel, right?
就像出租车行业垄断，不是吗？
Licenses gradually become guilds, where it is a matter of whether you can afford to buy [your way] into it.
许可证逐渐变成了行会， 这是一个您是否能负担的起的问题，您需要遵循
The quality standards, the certification, the regulation, the rules, all gradually disappear into the background.
质量标准，认证，规定，规则， 然后这些全部逐渐隐入幕后
The regulators stop doing those things and focus primarily on enforcing [entry into the market].
监管者不再做这些事情， 而将精力主要放在[进入市场资格]的审查
People forget why the rules exist. It simply becomes a professional guild.
人们忘记了规则存在的原因。 它只是成为一个专业行会
If you can afford to buy the necessary licenses, essentially bribe the government to allow you to work,
如果您有能力购买必要的许可证， 这实质上是贿赂政府以允许您工作
then you are part of the white market.
那么您就是白色市场的一部分
All white markets devolve into that state.
所有的白色市场都进入了这种状态
Over years, maybe decades or centuries, you arrive at absurd concentrations of wealth and power,
经过数年甚至数十年或几个世纪，您会看到财富和权力的荒唐的集中在一起
where you might have only seven families controlling every business in the country.
可能只有七个家族，就控制该国的所有业务
The fundamental differences between markets, white or black, should not be...
白色和黑色的市场之间的根本区别 ，不应...
measured by how well they are licensed.
由他们获得许可的程度来衡量
We should care about whether they are fair, open, and free.
我们应该在乎它们是否是公平，开放和免费的
In fact, if these markets are open and free, fairness arises as a result.
事实上，如果这些市场是开放的， 就会产生公平
If you don't like it, you can trade elsewhere. Competition ensures fairness.
如果您不喜欢这个地方的服务，可以在其他地方进行交易。 竞争确保公平
Here is the other subtle thing: absent a licensed white market, the state withdraws [any] services of justice.
这是另一件微妙的事情：如果是没有许可的白色市场，国家就不会提供任何司法服务
This is critical to understand.
这一点至关重要
Until now, the monopoly on the delivery of justice services existed primarily in the government's sphere.
迄今为止，对司法的垄断服务主要存在于政府领域
Let's use tech terms: goverments provided 'justice as a service' (JaaS).
让我们用技术术语来说：政府提供了“正义即服务”（JaaS）
Their 'justice as a service' API is only available for a certain fee to certain people, and it is usually broken.
他们的“正义即服务” API仅适用于已经收取了一定的费用的客户，并且通常是无效的
It [may] take seven years [or longer] to fulfill the request; nevertheless they offer 'justice as a service.'
可能需要7年[或更长时间]才能满足要求； 但是，他们提供“正义即服务”
But if you step outside of the white market, [your access to] 'justice as a service' is removed.
但是如果您走出白市， [您对[正义即服务]的访问权]被删除
You are exposed to the full risk of operating in a market where you have no justice [services from them],
您将承担在市场中经营的全部风险 在没有正义[他们提供的服务]的地方经营
where you have no recourse [facilities], no ability to settle disputes, and violence becomes the solution.
您没有追索权[办法]，没有能力解决争端，暴力成为解决之道
That happens even in white markets. I walked out of the airport here in Chile,
这甚至在白色市场也会发生， 我走出智利的机场
straight into a line of taxi drivers, who see me looking at my phone and say, "Uber?!" [Laughter]
出租车司机看到我在看手机， 就会说：“优步？！” [笑声]
[Backs away slowly] "Sorry!" What [should] I do then? Do I [alert] the police officer [about their behaviour]?
我[慢慢退开]“对不起！”那我该怎么办？ 我要提醒警察他们的行为吗？
No, because in every country I've been to, the cops are working with the taxi drivers...
不，因为我去过的每个国家 警察都会与出租车司机合作...
to beat up the Uber drivers and their passengers.
殴打优步司机及其乘客
Not only have they removed 'justice as a service,'
他们不仅删除了“正义即服务”，
they deliver injustice as a service [within] a [noncompetitive] blockade.
他们在[非竞争性]的封锁中提供不公正的服务
You don't go to the cops, because that is too dangerous. But I don't get my Uber ride, what is the big deal?
你不能去找警察，因为那太危险了。 但是我不坐Uber，有什么大不了的？
Think about all the markets in which 'justice as a service' has been removed,
想想所有的市场 ， 如果“正义即服务”已被取消
where you cannot enforce property rights; where [a currency exchange desk gives you] counterfeit money.
您无法行使财产权；在[货币兑换处给您]假币
Do you call the police? No, you don't call the police. You can't call the police. That service [was] removed.
你会报警吗？不，你不会报警。 你不能报警。该服务已被取消了
You have some funny situations,
你会遇到一些有趣的情况
like the [inexperienced] high school student trying to buy marijuana from some dude on the street.
就像[没有经验的]高中生尝试从大街上的某个家伙那里购买大麻
They get a bag of oregano [instead] and don't know the difference, so they think,
他们得到了一袋调料粉， 甚至不知道有什么区别，所以他们认为，
'I don't [know if] I should smoke this. Smells like a salad. Now what do I do? Do I call the cops? I can't call cops...'
“我不知道是否应该抽这个。它闻起来像沙拉。现在我该怎么办？我能叫警察吗？我不能叫警察...'
"Excuse me, sir. The illegal drugs I just bought are not correct!" Some people [actually] do that.
“对不起，先生。我刚买的违禁品质量不行！”有些人（实际上）会这样做
They go to the police and say, "This cocaine isn't good!" They soon discover that they [have a bigger] problem.
他们去报警，说：“可 卡 因质量不好！” 他们很快发现自己（有一个更大的问题）
Again, that's a little funny story and you might think they deserve what they get.
这又是一个有趣的故事， 您可能会认为他们这是罪有因得
After all, they are breaking the law and so they should be punished.
毕竟，他们违反了法律， 因此，他们应该受到惩罚
Now, think about the immigrant cleaner...
现在，考虑一下移民清洁工...
who had their passport taken from them by a coyote who [escorted] them across the border,
他们的护照被一个[护送]他们越过边界的地头蛇拿走了
now holding their passport hostage.
现在地头蛇拿着护照作为他们的质押
They are terrified to go to the police and live in a locked compound with bars on the windows.
他们很害怕去警察局， 被关在一个窗户上有栅栏的锁着的院子里
They cannot exercise their human rights, virtually kept as slaves within an industrialized society.
他们几乎不能行使自己的人权， 他们在工业化社会中被当作奴隶
That happens today, in the United States, to hundreds of thousands of people.
今天在美国 ,有成千上万的这样的人
Slavery is on the uptick all around the world. Why?
奴隶制在世界范围内呈上升趋势。为什么？
Being an illegal human being -- I don't even know what that means -- has resulted in...
作为一个非法入境的人-我甚至不懂--这意味着什么---是什么导致...
the removal of 'justice as a service' from entire categories of people.
为整整一个群体，取消“正义即服务”
Apply that to sex workers, engaging in acts of consensual sex or prostitution,
这种情况也发生在性工作者身上 在自愿的性行为或卖淫中，
even just people stripping and making funny movies.
甚至只是制作色情电影的人身上
They have no 'justice as a service.'
他们没有“正义即服务”
Violence, rape, and domestic abuse are massive problems in any illegal industry.
暴力，强奸和家暴也是这样， 在任何非法行业中都存在巨大问题
Black markets emerge where the need is great, where the demand causes an emergence of supply,
在需求很大的地方出现了黑市， 当需求导致供应时，
whether that is capital flight from Argentina, recreational drugs, or whatever else you might want to find.
无论是阿根廷的资本外逃，还是休闲娱乐毒品，或其他您可能想找到的东西
If there is no white market, the black market exists...
如果没有白市，就会出现黑市
but it charges a massive risk premium, sprinkled with a heavy dose of violence.
但它收取了巨大的风险溢价， 夹杂着大量暴力
Until now, justice could only be provided as a government service.
到目前为止，正义只能是作为一种政府服务提供
You cannot enforce property rights without a court of law... or can you?
如果没有法院，您不能执行财产权 ...还是可以？
What if we used a very large number, multiplied against another on an elliptic curve?
如果我们使用一个大质数， 在椭圆曲线上乘以另一个质数？
[What if, in combination with other factors], that crazy idea [of computer science and math]...
[如果结合其他因素，可以解决这个问题吗？ 那是个[计算机科学和数学家]的疯狂主意...
would allow me to enforce global property rights?
那可以让我执行全球财产权吗？
What if I could use a smart contract in order to create a matching service between buyers and sellers,
如果我可以使用智能合约以便创建买卖双方之间的匹配服务，
that ensures there is no forgery, no fraud?
确保没有伪造，没有欺诈？
What if I could use a smart contract to escrow money in the process of buying any product?
如果我可以在购买任何产品的过程中，使用智能合约托管资金，会怎么样？
Now I can ensure [people] don't get cheated.
那么，我可以确保[人们]不会被欺骗
What if I could use a smart contract [for] reputation services like Uber does, giving me a degree of comfort...
如果我可以使用智能合约来记录声誉，会怎么样？ 像Uber这样的服务，给我一定的信任...
without the centralized company?
没有集权的公司？
What if I could get 'justice as a service' from a network?
如果我可以从网络获得“正义即服务”会怎么样？
That is what happened. The world has changed. It is not a distinction between the licensed market,
就是这样，世界已经改变。 这不是许可市场之间的区别，
where you have some justice, and the unlicensed market, where you have no justice.
老黄历是，有执照的市场就有公正， 没有执照的无牌市场就没有公正
Bitcoin doesn't care. Ethereum doesn't care. [Open] blockchains don't see colors.
而比特币不在乎。以太坊不在乎。 [开放的]区块链看不到市场的颜色
They don't see borders and they don't see [authorities]. They only see rules.
他们看不到边界，他们看不到[当局]。他们只看到规则
They can deliver 'justice as a service' no matter what color your market is: white, black, or grey.
他们可以提供“正义即服务” 无论您的市场是什么颜色：白色，黑色或灰色。
Bitcoin, Ethereum, [and other open blockchains] serve markets wherever there is supply and demand.
比特币，以太坊和[和其他开放式区块链] 服务于有供求关系的市场
They serve markets globally, without distinction for borders.
他们为全球市场服务， 不分国界
Here is another little secret you don't remember:
这里还有一个您不记得的小秘密：
state 'justice as a service' only applies within a specific geography.
“正义即服务”仅仅适用于特定地理位置
The Chilean justice provider only works within the borders of Chile.
智利司法人员只能在智利境内工作
What can you do with that [limitation] as an individual? Not much. What can multi-national companies do?
作为个人，您可以做什么？ 并不多。跨国公司可以做什么？
They can screw you in a hundred and ninety-four different countries.
他们可以在九十四个不同的国家欺骗你
Unless they are in [the same jurisdiction as you], you don't have much recourse.
除非他们和您在[同一司法管辖区]，否则您没有多少追索权
Then again, they [may have] also bought your legislators, so you don't have recourse in that one either.
再说一次，他们（可能）也收买了你的立法者，因此，您在自己的国家可能也没有多少追索权
Blockchain 'justice as a service' works globally.
而区块链“正义即服务”在全球范围内有效
It doesn't care whether you are inside or outside that border.
不在乎你是否在该边界之内或之外
The other little [secret] we often forget: when people say a product is illegal, your first question should be:
我们常常忘记的另一个小秘密：当人们 说某产品是违法的，您的第一个问题应该是：
"Illegal where?" 'Legal' and 'illegal' are geography-bound terms. Illegal where?
“在哪里是非法的？” “合法”和“非法”是受地理位置限制的字词。在哪里是非法的？
Illegal here? What if I'm not here, but in another country? Is it legal there? These are highly relative notions.
这里不合法吗？如果我不在这里，但在另一个国家会怎么样？在那里就合法吗？这些是高度相对的概念
They imply a strong morality component that you may not share. Is it legal to buy a Bible?
它们暗示着强大的道德成分， 您可能不会认同这些道德。买圣经合法吗？
In Saudi Arabia, it's not. In Saudi Arabia, it was also illegal to drive unless you fulfill both requirements:
在沙特阿拉伯就是非法的。在沙特阿拉伯， 除非您同时满足以下两个条件，否则就是非法驾驶：
a driver's license and a penis. [Laughter] Well, until recently. They fixed that one.
驾驶执照和阴茎。 [笑声] 好吧，直到最近。他们修正了那个
Now you can drive without [the second] one.
现在，您无需[第二个]即可拥有驾驶资格
But you might still get beaten up by the cops, because they are "protecting their morality." Not my morality.
但是您可能仍然会被警察殴打，因为他们正在“捍卫自己的道德”。不是我的道德
Is it legal to buy certain substances? Is it legal to buy bombs to [attack] another country?
购买某些物质合法吗？ 购买炸弹袭击另一个国家合法吗？
Again, legality is bound by geography [and authority].
同样，合法性受地理[和权力]的约束
Blockchains are not. With the blockchain, you can enforce justice across borders.
区块链可不是这样。有了区块链， 您可以跨境执行正义
You can enforce justice across the world, whether you consider the markets within the narrow...
您可以在世界各地执行正义， 您无需考虑狭窄的市场...
scope of your own country [to be] white or black, grey or blue.
无需考虑在你自己国家的范围里是白色或黑色，灰色或蓝色的
Blockchains serve justice. They can deliver free, open, and fair markets worldwide.
区块链服务正义。他们可以提供 全球范围内的自由，开放和公平的市场
Does that mean you can use blockchains for the black market? Hell yes, it does.
这是否意味着您可以使用区块链进入黑市？当然，确实如此
There is a demand for that. To make white markets better? Yes. And every [color] in between? Yes.
这是有需求的。进入白色市场是否更容易？ 当然。进入每个[颜色]的市场呢？没问题
It is not about white. It is not about black. It is about free, open, and fair. Thank you!
它不是关于白色的市场。它不是关于黑色的市场。它是关于自由，开放和公平的。谢谢！
[Applause]
[掌声]
[AUDIENCE] Hello. It is really great to be able to see you live, after all these years.
[观众]您好。这么多年了，看到您的演讲，真的很棒
My question is, how will you be able to enforce 'justice as a service' from a blockchain?
我的问题是，您将如何执行来自区块链的“正义即服务”？
There is a monopoly on force, but there is also a judge, [who have judicial monopolies] in the state.
武力可以保证垄断，但法官[拥有司法垄断权]的人也可以保证
[ANDREAS] Again, the word "enforcement" contains the word "force," but does it have to [in practice]?
[ANDREAS]同样，“执法”一词包含“武力”一词，但是在实践中这是必须的吗？
How much of our current commercial transactions really require that level of recourse, where you have force?
我们目前实际进行的商业交易中，有多少交易要求这种级别的追索权？
Force can be applied to a certain degree, but once you try to apply it to too many people, too many things,
可以在一定程度上施加武力，但是一旦您尝试将其施加于太多的人，太多的事物，
for too many reasons...
由于太多原因...
You [must] pay people to apply the force, and by that time you have messed your currency up so well...
您[必须]付钱给人们以施加力量， 到那时，您已经把您的货币政策搞得一团糟
that you can't pay the enforcers.
你不能付钱给执法者
In Venezuela, for example. I watched a great video the other day, which showed some enforcers for Maduro...
以委内瑞拉为例。前几天，我看了一段精彩的视频，其中显示了马杜罗的一些执法人员...
smiling in front of a camera, holding the privileges of their position, which were two toilet paper rolls.
在镜头前微笑， 手里拿着两个卫生纸卷
That is how low payment for the enforcement service [has become].
执法服务的收费[已成为]非常低
How far away [are they] from the moment when they [decide], 'This is not worth it!'
当他们[决定]“这不值得！”的时候，他们离那一刻有多远，
Enforcement and force are aspects of the human condition and society.
执法和武力是人类状况和社会的两个方面
What we are talking about here is enforcing justice...
我们在这里谈论的是执行正义
through rules agreed on by everyone in a consensus system without violence.
通过每个人都同意的规则, 不需要暴力的共识体系
This is a non-violent mechanism for enforcement. It is primarily financial enforcement.
这是一种非暴力的执行机制。 主要是金融上的执法
It works through a series of incentives and punishments, game theory.
它通过一系列激励措施起作用 还有惩罚，博弈论
What we found through markets and game theory is that those [non-violent] mechanisms work better.
我们通过市场和博弈论发现: 这些[非暴力]机制运作得更好
They don't expect people to be good, they only expect people to act in their self-interest.
他们不期望别人都是好人， 他们只期望人们为自己的利益而行动
If everybody acts in their self-interest in a system of rules that punish bad and reward good behaviour,
如果每个人都在系统中为自身利益行事 惩罚不良行为并奖励良好行为的规则，
then good behaviour emerges naturally from the system.
然后，良好的行为会自然而然的从这个体系中产生
I don't know how well it [will] work, but let's build some things and test them out.
我不知道它的效果如何， 但是让我们构建一些东西并对其进行测试
I certainly know, one of the beautiful things about operating on digital platforms, one of the reasons...
我当然知道， 在数字平台上运行的美妙之处之一，原因之一...
why people want to run drug markets on the internet, is because you cannot be stabbed over TCP/IP.
人们为什么要在互联网上经营毒品市场， 这是因为他们无法通过TCP / IP 伤害您
[ORGANISER] Next question? I think there was one in the back.
[组织者]下一个问题？ 我认为后面还有一个问题
[AUDIENCE] Hi, I want to ask you about black markets, white markets, and banks.
[观众]嗨，我想问您一个问题 ， 有关于黑市，白市和银行的
[ANDREAS] Yes. [AUDIENCE] We have so many problems with banks "de-risking."
[ANDREAS]好的。 [观众]我们有 银行“去风险化”的许多问题
Let me know what you think about that, because it is part of [how they keep control].
让我知道您对此有何想法， 因为这是[他们保持控制力的方式]的一部分
[ANDREAS] Well, that is the final culmination of a white market.
[ANDREAS]好，那就是最后的结果，白色市场的高潮部分
When the rules that start off as "consumer protection" eventually become "banker protection."
当开始制定“保护消费者”的规则时， 这最终成为“保护银行家”
As a result, they become protection from competition, which leads to a guild.
最终，它们成为一个竞争的保护伞，变成一个行业协会
Once a guild is powerful and organised enough, we have a different word for that. It is called a cartel.
一旦一个公会强大而有组织， 对此我们有不同的说法。它被称为卡特尔
We don't use the word "cartel" to refer to banks, because they have such a big cartel. [Laughter]
我们不使用“ cartel”一词来指代银行， 因为他们已经变成了这么大的卡特尔。 [笑声]
Banks no longer serve many of the important functions that you would expect the banks to serve.
银行不再履行您期望的许多重要职能
They don't [even] bank people. The number of unbanked is not decreasing, twenty-five years into the internet.
他们甚至都不会服务一些人。 进入互联网已有25年了，未开户的人群数量并没有减少
They are not serving [more people]. I was [giving a talk] at a security conference that was full of bankers.
他们没有为[更多的人]服务。 我当时在在一个坐满银行家的安全会议上演讲
I was describing how bitcoin, as a form of money, can serve populations that are doing remittances...
我当时在描述比特币如何作为一种货币， 可以为正在汇款的人群服务...
to foreign countries, but who don't have bank accounts because they are not properly documented.
到国外，为那些没有银行账户的人服务， 因为他们没有证明文件
They are illegal immigrants or migrants into a country.
他们是非法移民或移民到一个国家
As a result, they can't open a bank account and pay enormous fees...
结果，他们因为无法开设银行帐户并支付巨额费用...
to be robbed by the grey market of Western Union and [various] check cashing services.
被西联汇款和[各种]支票兑现服务的灰色市场抢劫
During my presentation, this lady in the back asked, "But why should we give bank accounts to illegals?"
在我的演讲中，后面的这位女士问： “但是为什么我们要为违法者开设银行账户呢？”
At least half of the people in the room were decent enough to gasp. [Laughter]
房间里至少有一半的体面人 倒抽一口冷气。 [笑声]
But the other half were really interested in the answer, so I said, "No, you shouldn't. Don't. We will." [Applause]
但是另一半对答案很感兴趣， 所以我说：“不，你不应该。你不用。我们会的。” [掌声]
[ORGANISER] Okay, one more question? [AUDIENCE] Hi, Andreas. [ANDREAS] Hello.
[组织者]好的，还有一个问题吗？ [观众]嗨，安德里亚斯。 [ANDREAS]您好。
[AUDIENCE] It is a pleasure to meet you, thank you for being a great teacher and inspiring everyone.
[观众]很高兴认识您，谢谢您，您是一名出色的老师并激励了所有人
My question is about blockchains, not in general but as an educator myself.
我的问题是关于区块链的， 不是关于一般人，而是作为一个教育者
I am trying to battle every start-up that says "blockchain" without [using] a blockchain or [doing] decentralisation,
我正在努力与每个说“区块链”的初创企业抗衡，他们其实没有[使用]区块链或[去]去中心化，
disintermediation, just a database.
或者去中介化，它们只是一个数据库
What is [your] recommendation for us to battle that movement?
关于我们与这些炒作的斗争，您有什么建议？
To call everything "blockchain" while not doing anything innovative or decentralised?
把“区块链”联系到一切上面， 而不是做任何创新或去中心化的事情？
[ANDREAS] You don't need to "battle" anything. What you need to do is just remove your attention...
[ANDREAS]您无需为任何事情“战斗”。 您需要做的就是消除您的注意力...
and interest from these projects, because they serve no purpose.
和这些项目的兴趣，因为他们没有用
You [must] ask yourself, when you hear that someone's project has "blockchain"-
您[必须]问自己，当某人的项目使用了“区块链”
Well, nowadays what they usually say is: "We are introducing a revolutionary new system."
好吧，如今他们通常说的是： “我们正在引入一种革命性的新系统。”
"Blockchain, artificial intelligence, and internet-of-things, using neural networks to [magic noise] give me money."
“区块链，人工智能和物联网， 用神经网络[神奇的噪音]给我钱。”
At that point, you [should] stop listening or ask, "Is it borderless, open, neutral, global, censorship resistant?"
在这一点上，您[应该]不要听，而是问：“它是无国界，开放，中立，全球性，不受审查制度影响的吗？”
If it is not, you don't need a blockchain. Those are the features provided by open, decentralized blockchains.
如果不是，则不需要区块链。 那些是开放，去中心化区块链提供的功能
Ask those five questions, ask for the five pillars. If it is none of those things, then it is just a database.
提出这五个问题，提出五个支柱。 如果这些都不是，那么它只是一个数据库
It is a centralized and very inefficient, slow, expensive database that is difficult to develop...
它是集中式的，非常低效，缓慢，昂贵的数据库，难以开发...
and has a really shitty user interface.
并具有非常糟糕的用户界面
In the era of Microsoft databases and Oracle, it takes a lot of effort to produce an even shittier interface.
在Microsoft数据库和Oracle时代， 为了创造一个更糟糕的界面而付出了很多努力。
The bottom line is, this is not a good solution for anything if you are not looking for those features.
底线是，这不是一个好的解决方案 如果您不需要这些功能，则可以进行任何操作
Do you need to fight that market [of bullshit blockchain projects]? No, don't fight it.
您是否需要与[这些狗屁区块链项目]竞争？ 不，不要反抗
Let them spend $100 million training developers and consultants in this industry, while producing bullshit.
让他们花费1亿美元培训开发人员， 以及这个行业的顾问，同时制造废品
Once that project fails, those developers will look around and [wonder], 'What do we do now?'
一旦该项目失败，这些开发人员将环顾四周并[思考]，“我们现在要做什么？”
'I heard about this other project, I would like to work on that.'
``我听说过另一个项目，我想为此努力
And then they go work on a real open-source, decentralized blockchain. I [was] saying this in 2013,
然后他们开始在真正的开源上、去中心化区块链项目上工作，我在2013年这样说，
that [banks] will [pay to] train developers and those developers will discover Bitcoin and open blockchains.
[银行]将[支付]培训开发商和那些开发人员，帮助他们发现比特币并开放区块链的重要性
[They will think], 'These are much more interesting projects.' When I was visiting Singapore, it happened.
[他们会认为]，“这些是有趣得多的项目“。当我访问新加坡时，它就这样发生了
I sat down next to a kid who said to me, "I'm really excited, this is my first Bitcoin conference."
我坐在一个小孩子旁边，他对我说：“我真的很高兴，这是我第一次参加比特币会议。”
"I watched one of your videos."
“我看了你的一部视频。”
"You know... I have been working with blockchains for a year, but I had not heard about Bitcoin until yesterday."
“你知道...今年我一直在做区块链相关的工作，但直到昨天我才听说比特币。”
[Taken aback] [Laughter] I asked, "What? How? Tell me more, I want to hear!"
[我大吃一惊] [众笑]我问：“什么？ 你说什么？告诉我更多的情况，我想听听！”
[He said], "A year ago, I went to this presentation by Bank of America about decentralized ledger technology."
[他说]，“一年前，我参加了美国银行的关于分布式分类帐技术的讲演”
"Eventually, at some point in the slides, they mentioned the 'b' word." Not Bitcoin, but "blockchain."
“最终，在幻灯片的某个位置， 提到了“ b”打头这个词。”不是比特币，而是“区块链”。
"They told us this would be the greatest technology."
“他们告诉我们这将是最伟大的技术。”
"They managed to go through all thirty slides without mentioning the other 'b' word at all."
“他们浏览了全部三十张幻灯片 完全不提另一个“ b”字。”
This person worked with Hyperledger, R3, and all of these other companies in the "DLT space."
此人曾与Hyperledger，R3和“ DLT空间”中的所有其他公司有合作关系
And those were... interesting, but not that interesting. Then one day, they discovered Bitcoin and thought,
那些东西很有趣，但没那么有趣。 然后有一天，他们发现了比特币并想，
'Whoa! This is where it came from? This seems very weird and a bit exciting!' [Laughter]
“哇！这是哪里来的项目？好像很奇怪，有点刺激！ [笑声]
And we gained one more developer, perfectly trained and ready to go.
于是我们又增加了一位开发人员 他训练有素，随时准备出发
They just needed to re-learn some basic concepts, and they are good to go on a nice open-source project.
他们只需要重新学习一些基本概念， 他们很乐意参与一个不错的开源项目
Don't fight that market.
不要打击那个市场
Let them waste bank money on trying to co-opt and distort the ideas of what we're building,
让他们把银行的钱浪费在试图吸收和扭曲我们正在建设的理念上；
then run straight into the wall of their centralized, sclerotic, dinosaur organisations.
直到他们撞墙； 变成集中的，僵化的，过时的组织
Then the project fails to deliver anything and gets chopped by the board of directors,
然后项目无法交付任何东西 并被董事会砍掉，
who are no longer impressed by the word 'blockchain.'
他们不再对“区块链”一词印象深刻
The people [from that project] take their Christmas bonus [and use it to open] a start-up in January,
这个（项目）的人会拿着他们的圣诞奖金 （并用它来开设）在一月份的初创企业，
in order to compete with [their former bank bosses].
为了与[他们的前银行老板]竞争
[The banks] pay for their own demise. [Applause] [ORGANISER] Thank you so much! Time is up.
[银行]为自己的灭亡支付费用。 [掌声] [组织者]非常感谢！时间到了。
[ANDREAS] For the people who asked questions, please come and see me at the edge of the stage here.
[ANDREAS]对于提出问题的人， 请过来在舞台的边上来见我
I would like to give you a copy of my book, 'Internet del Dinero,' the Spanish edition of ['The Internet of Money'].
我想给你一本我的书，西班牙语版的《互联网货币》（The Internet of Money）
I will be signing books tomorrow after the fireside chat; [you can] see me then, I would be happy to sign [them].
我明天会在炉边闲聊，在书上签名。 您如果遇到我，我很乐意签名
Thank you so much! [Applause] [ORGANISER] We want you to sign something else.
非常感谢！ [掌声] [组织者]我们希望您签署一点其他东西
This is [art of] you as 'Mr. Bitcoin Superman.' We will auction this off on the last day of the conference.
这是您作为'比特币超人”的艺术品， 我们会在会议的最后一天进行拍卖
For a good cause. [ANDREAS] Fantastic! [ORGANISER] Made by artist Luis Buenaventura.
有一个很好的理由。 [ANDREAS]太棒了！ [组织者]这是由艺术家路易斯·布埃纳文图拉（Luis Buenaventura）创作的
[ORGANISER] Please sign it with your 'private key.' [ANDREAS] My pleasure. [Laughter]
[组织者]请使用您的“私钥”签名。 [安德烈亚斯]我的荣幸。 [笑声]